Morand, Martin papers 6036/079
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Martin Morand papers
1950-2010
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Morand, Martin
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
6036/079
1.11 cubic feet
1.1 linear ft.
Papers.
This collection consists of Martin Morand's correspondence, writings, and collected printed material, documenting his work with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union and Professor of Industrial and Labor Relations at Indiana University of Pennsylvania.
7289211
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, August 29, 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 30, 2015
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Martin Morand was born in New York City on December 18, 1927, and raised in the Amalgamated Housing Cooperative in the Bronx. He began college at the City College of New York in 1944, while working (and a member of the Office and Professional Employees International Union). Morand transferred to the School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell.
After graduating in 1948, Morand began as an ILGWU organizer in Pennsylvania. From 1964 to 1969, he served as Director of the ILGWU's Southeast Region. After leaving the ILGWU, he worked for the AFL-CIO Staff Training Center, AFSCME, and National Education Association (NEA). In 1976, he helped to establish the master's degree program in Industrial and Labor Relations at Indiana University of Pennsylvania; Morand taught in that program until his retirement in 2000.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, letters written by Morand, and printed email messages, as well as articles and histories he had written and collected. The majority of the collection consists of material during Morand's tenure with the ILGWU. Included are the newsletters "UNITE! Insight," and the ILGWU "Southeaster News" and the "Southern Garment Worker," which were published bi-monthly by the Southeast Region, of which Morand was director. Morand wrote the "Director's Column," which was a column that appeared in those publications. There are also various publications from ILGW departments and locals in Pennsylvania. Morand collected numerous clippings and copies of articles that discuss the union or that mention himself. Also available is a DVD of an oral history interview entitled "Martin Morand: Labor and Social Activist" recorded in Santa Fe, New Mexico on May 13, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/058: ILGWU Southeast Region Records
Morand, Martin J.
7289211
- Martin Morand: Labor and Social Activist, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  May 13, 2008. DVD. Interview by Chicago Radical Jewish Elders program
- Correspondence, 1998-2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Also includes undated correspondence
- Writings (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Primarily related to ILGWU. Also collected document. Undated.
- Negotiations Workbook (Box 1, Folder 4)
  n.d.
- "My Name Is Mary Brown", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  songs from the ILGWU musical narrative performed at Golden Jubilee Convention
- UNITE! Insight, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Publication of UNITE Northeast, Western Pennyslvania, and Ohio Department
- Southeastern News, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Publication of ILGWU Southeast Department
- Southern Garment Worker, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Southern Garment Worker, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Pennsylvania ILGWU publications, 1963-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Copies (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Folder closed to researchers (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Unpublished article by Yevette Richards. Contact author for permission to access.
- Notes for Cheryl - Dominican Republic invasion 1965 Convention (Box 2, Folder 1)
- ILGWU South; MJM Missing People 1-3, Ben Stein Comments; Seniority, Work-sharing; Union of Offices; DD + South + Race; Morand/MaCoy (Box 2, Folder 2)
- ILG PA - Testimonials (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Martin Morand: Labor and Social Activist - May 13, 2008 (Box 3)